Dr Victor Maus

Senior Researcher

Curriculum Vitae Jänner 2022

• Welthandelsplatz 1, 1020 Vienna, Austria

☆ victor-maus.com +43 1 31336 6176 vwmaus1@gmail.com

@victor_maus vwmaus

in victor-maus-083a79191 **G** wN2LseQAAAAJ&hl 0000-0002-7385-4723

Victor Maus is a researcher at the Institute for Ecological Economics from Vienna University of Economics and Business (WU), Austria. He also works as a research scholar at the International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis (IIASA) in Laxenburg, Austria, since 2016. His research contributes to methodological developments in geoinformatics and spatial data science for sustainable development, particularly related to land-use changes. His main early achievements include the development of a pattern recognition algorithm called Time-Weighted Dynamic Time Warping (TWDTW) to classify satellite image time series in data-scarce conditions and the production of the first global map of mining activities. Maus has published his research in leading international journals such as Global Environmental Change, Nature Scientific Data, and the Journal of Statistical Software.

ACADEMIC CAREER

2018-Today	Senior researcher in geoinformatics Vienna University of Economics and Business (WU)	Vienna, Austria
2016-Today	Research scholar in Earth observation data analytics International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis (IIASA)	Laxenburg, Austria
2014-2016	Research assistant in big geospatial data analytics University of Münster (WWU)	Münster, Germany
Jun - Aug/2013	Research assistant International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis (IIASA), Young Scientist	Laxenburg, Austria Summer Program (YSSP)
2012-2014	University lecturer in science and technology Federal University of Pampa (UNIPAMPA)	Itaqui, Brazil
2011-2012	Research assistant in remote sensing National Institute for Space Research (INPE)	São José dos Campos, Brazil
2009-2011	Research assistant computational modelling Federal University of Juiz de Fora (UFJF)	Juiz de Fora, Brazil

EDUCATION

2016	PhD in Earth System Science	São José dos Campos, Brazil
	National Institute for Space Research (INPE)	
2011	MSc in Computational Modeling Federal University of Juiz de Fora (UFJF)	Juiz de Fora, Brazil
2009	BSc in Environmental Engineering	Santa Maria, Brazil

Franciscan University (UFN)

AWARDS

2022 Researcher of the month award Vienna, Austria Vienna University of Economics and Business (WU)

TRAINING

2020	Communication training – Speaking with Confidence and Impact Vienna University of Economics and Business (WU)	Vienna, Austria
2019	Pedagogical training – The basics of teaching and learning in higher education	Vienna, Austria

Vienna University of Economics and Business (WU)

2019	Leadership training – Setting people in motion: leading and motivating your team Vienna University of Economics and Business (WU)	Vienna, Austria
2013	Pedagogical Treating - University teaching: methods and evaluation Federal University of Pampa (UNIPAMPA)	Itaqui, Brazil

RESEARCH GRANTS FELLOWSHIPS

2014-2016	Research Assistant University of Münster (WWU)	Münster, Germany
2012-2014	University Lecturer Federal University of Pampa (UNIPAMPA)	Itaqui, Brazil
2011-2012	Research Assistant National Institute for Space Research (INPE)	São José dos Campos, Brazil
2009-2011	Research Assistant Federal University of Juiz de Fora (UFJF)	Juiz de Fora, Brazil

SUPERVISION OF STUDENTS

2014-2016	Research Assistant University of Münster (WWU)	Münster, Germany
2012-2014	University Lecturer Federal University of Pampa (UNIPAMPA)	Itaqui, Brazil
2011-2012	Research Assistant National Institute for Space Research (INPE)	São José dos Campos, Brazil
2009-2011	Research Assistant Federal University of Juiz de Fora (UFJF)	Juiz de Fora, Brazil

TEACHING ACTIVITIES INSTITUTIONAL RESPONSIBILITIES REVIEWING ACTIVITIES

PUBLICATIONS

- 1. Luckeneder, S., Giljum, S., Schaffartzik, A., Maus, V., & Tost, M. (2021). Surge in global metal mining threatens vulnerable ecosystems. *Global Environmental Change*, 69, 102303. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2021. 102303
- 2. Maus, V., Giljum, S., Gutschlhofer, J., Silva, D. M. da, Gass, S. L. B., Luckeneder, S., Lieber, M., & McCallum, I. (2020). A global-scale data set of mining areas. *Scientific Data*, 7(1), 289. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-020-00624-w
- 3. Bruckner, M., Wood, R., Moran, D., Kuschnig, N., Wieland, H., **Maus, V.**, & Börner, J. (2019). FABIO-the construction of the food and agriculture biomass input-output model. *Environmental Science & Technology*, *53*(19), 11302–11312. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.9b03554
- 4. Stanimirova, R., Arévalo, P., Kaufmann, R. K., **Maus, V.**, Lesiv, M., Havlík, P., & Friedl, M. A. (2019). Sensitivity of global pasturelands to climate variation. *Earth's Future*. https://doi.org/10.1029/2019EF001316
- 5. Maus, V., Câmara, G., Appel, M., & Pebesma, E. (2019). dtwSat: Time-Weighted Dynamic Time Warping for Satellite Image Time Series Analysis in R. *Journal of Statistical Software*, 88(5), 1–31. https://doi.org/10.18637/jss.v088.i05
- 6. Bruckner, M., Häyhä, T., Giljum, S., **Maus, V**., Fischer, G., Tramberend, S., & Börner, J. (2019). Quantifying the global cropland footprint of the european union's non-food bioeconomy. *Environmental Research Letters*, 14(4), 045011. https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/ab07f5
- 7. Hadi, Krasovskii, A., **Maus, V.**, Yowargana, P., Pietsch, S., & Rautiainen, M. (2018). Monitoring Deforestation in Rainforests Using Satellite Data: A Pilot Study from Kalimantan, Indonesia. *Forests*, 9(7). https://doi.org/10.3390/f9070389

- 8. See, L., Laso Bayas, J. C., Schepaschenko, D., Perger, C., Dresel, C., Maus, V., Salk, C., Weichselbaum, J., Lesiv, M., McCallum, I., Moorthy, I., & Fritz, S. (2017). LACO-Wiki: A New Online Land Cover Validation Tool Demonstrated Using GlobeLand30 for Kenya. *Remote Sensing*, 9(7). https://doi.org/10.3390/rs9070754
- 9. Furlan, V. J. M., **Maus, V**., Batista, I., & Bandarra, N. M. (2017). Production of docosahexaenoic acid by Auranti-ochytrium sp. ATCC PRA-276. *Brazilian Journal of Microbiology*, 48(2), 359–365. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bjm. 2017.01.001
- 10. **Maus, V.**, Camara, G., Cartaxo, R., Sanchez, A., Ramos, F. M., & Queiroz, G. R. de. (2016). A time-weighted dynamic time warping method for land-use and land-cover mapping. *IEEE Journal of Selected Topics in Applied Earth Observations and Remote Sensing*, *9*(8), 3729–3739. https://doi.org/10.1109/JSTARS.2016.2517118
- 11. Furlan, V. J. M., Castelo Paulo, M. do, **Maus, V**., Ferreira, J., Batista, I., & Bandarrac, N. M. (2016). Production of docosahexaenoic acid (DHA) from Thraustochytrium sp. ATCC 26185 using different nitrogen concentrations. *Boletim Centro de Pesquisa de Processamento de Alimentos*, 34(2), 1–11. https://doi.org/10.5380/cep.v34i2. 53189
- See, L., Schepaschenko, D., Lesiv, M., McCallum, I., Fritz, S., Comber, A., Perger, C., Schill, C., Zhao, Y., Maus, V., Siraj, M. A., Albrecht, F., Cipriani, A., Vakolyuk, M., Garcia, A., Rabia, A. H., Singha, K., Marcarini, A. A., Kattenborn, T., ... Obersteiner, M. (2015). Building a hybrid land cover map with crowdsourcing and geographically weighted regression. *ISPRS Journal of Photogrammetry and Remote Sensing*, 103, 48–56. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isprsjprs.2014.06.016
- 13. Maus, V., Costa, A. B. da, & Righes, A. A. (2009). Tratamento do lixiviado de aterro de resíduos sólidos urbanos por processo fenton. *Tecno-Lógica*, 13(1), 52–59. https://doi.org/10.17058/tecnolog.v13i1.931